Preliminary Guide to the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Institute for Mediterranean Affairs records
1940-1980
MS 1688
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
47.25
The records consist of subject files, correspondence, administrative files, and publications documenting the activities of the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs.
Institute for Mediterranean Affairs
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Palestine Statehood Committee: "Concerning the campaigns for a Jewish Army; to save the Jewish people of Europe and the establishment of a Hebrew Republic in Palestine" Papers, MS 690. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
The Institute for Mediterranean Affairs was chartered by the University of the State of New York. It focused on developing an understanding of the historical and contemporary political and socio-economic problems of regions that border the Mediterranean Sea, especially the Middle East and North Africa.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of subject files, correspondence, administrative files, and publications documenting the activities of the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs.
The Answer; Jews; World War, 1939-1945; Zionism; Africa, North; Israel; Middle East; Palestine; Hebrew Committee of National Liberation; Institute for Mediterranean Affairs; Irgun tsevaʼi leʼumi
- Inventory
  - "US Foreign Policy in the Near East" [study prepared for U.S. Senate by IMA], 1959; writings on Jews in Europe in World War II, undated (Box 1)
  - Subject files, HCNL [Hebrew Committee of National Liberation], repatriation - zionism, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Subject files, HCNL, M - P; advertisements; photographs, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 3)
  - Card file, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s-1980s, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 6)
  - Subject files, M - Z, 1970s-1980s (Box 7)
  - Dramatis persona files, A - B, undated
  - Subject files, HCNL, Begin - Committee for a Jewish Army (Box 8)
  - Subject files, G - M (Box 9)
  - Writings [miscellaneous] (Box 10)
  - HCNL files, August 1946 - June 1947 (Box 11)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 12)
  - IMA correspondence files, A - Z, 1980s
  - Subject files, A - F
  - FBI files on HCNL, Free Palestine, et al (Box 13)
  - Persona dramatis, C - Z; From Solution to Problem, drafts of chapters (Box 14)
  - British Foreign Office, United States Department of State, documents (Box 15)
  - Person files, A - M, 1970s-1980s (Box 16)
  - Writings, publications (Box 17–18)
  - Person files, M - Z (Box 19)
  - American Jewish Commission, 1981-1984 (Box 20)
  - Publications
  - Administrative files, 1950s-1980s (Box 21)
  - Subject files on Hecht, Irgun, Jabotinsky (Box 22)
  - Writings, subject files [labeled "duplicates"] (Box 23)
  - Dan Nimrod, 1980s (Box 24)
  - AFL-CIO newsletter, 1980s
  - FBI files, 1945
  - Subject files
    - A - C, 1960s (Box 25)
    - F - U, 1970s-1980s
  - Subject, person files, writings, 1940s-1970s (Box 26)
  - Files labeled November 1942 - April 1944 [ photocopies] (Box 27)
  - Files labeled May 1944 - July 1945 (Box 28)
  - Without A Mandate, source materials [labeled Documentary Record], 1940s-1980s (Box 29)
  - Files labeled July 1947 - December 1948, 1949, 1950-1962 (Box 30)
  - Card files, 1940s-1970s (Box 31–32)
  - Documentary Record notebooks, speeches (Box 33)
  - Card files, people files, magazines, 1970s, undated (Box 34–35)
  - Subject files, C - H, 1970s-1980s (Box 36)
  - Publications, magazines, Irgun materials, 1940s-1970s (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - Publications, IMA (Box 39)
  - The Answer, 1943-1946 (Box 40)
  - Photocopies of materials from other archives (Box 41)
  - HCNL files, August 1945 - July 1946 (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 43)
  - HCNL files, 1938 - October 1942 (Box 44)
  - US State Department, FBI, OSS documents, 1940s
  - Subject files, 1940s, 1980s (Box 45)
  - Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 46)
  - Photographs; miscellaneous
  - The Answer, 1944-1948 (Box 47–49)
  - Newspapers, miscellaneous, 1943-1948 (Box 50–54)